[Music]
welcome to busy cental lunch event uh
about 2024 release wave two my name is
Alexander toic and I will try to explain
what is new in uh sustainability
management for this
release um you see first I will remind
you about some basic things about
introduction because we just started
previous wave with this new feature
uh after that I will explain what is new
here to make some small overview and
then the most of time I will demo all
these new features here on the end I
will just take few few minutes maybe
just one minute to explain our current
Mar Market position about this module
and bus
Central okay uh What uh plans we had
when we started we wanted first to build
U sustainability feature embedded inside
the uh busy Central uh idea was to have
a new feature for all busy Central
existing users for future users but
again idea was to make uh some
sustainability for SMB feature for non
busy Central users at all so it can be
used without any other feature busy
central idea was to provide Dynamic
calculations um to make it easier for uh
calculating emissions to provide better
visualization to to have some basic apis
to make some
forecast and and uh with the future
releases we will plus add some
additional features required for
reporting about Waste Water Management
but idea was to make proper um
collaboration tool for isv so we enabled
apis we tried to encourage our partners
to build their industry specific
vertical Solutions so it was our main
plan you can find all our documentation
AK Ms BCG so everything what is done uh
so far is there explain details so let's
remind how we how did we start um just
six months ago we decided to start just
with fundamentals we didn't want to try
to deliver everything in one way this is
not possible we didn't want we wanted to
build proper Foundation part so
fundamentals will be good enough to
enable us for building new Advanced
features on this module so what we
provide we provide the chart to
sustainability accounts where you can uh
Define your emissions with across the c
one two or three then you had categories
subcategories with uh embedded formulas
you can eventually add your own formulas
there you can extend it uh you can
Define what emissions you want to track
if you have emission factors you can
Define them on subcategories then we had
sustainability journals both standard
and recurring and when you post
everything what you had in your journals
we finish in sustainability Ledger
entries we provided additional three uh
reports with the xcl outs to make it
easier for tracking uh progress to see
what you are doing about sustainability
and to make it easier as this is
definitely new area for the most of for
the most I think absolutely majority of
users we provided proper demo data so
you can start testing
immediately and now let's see what we
deliver this way because there are a lot
of questions okay if we will stop only
with fundamentals and we promised we
will not stop we want to enable new
features and with this wave um how we
decided what we'll deliver we made a lot
of research what is the most important
for partners for customers and we
couldn't deliver everything of course in
one wave but we made some order what is
the most important and we try to go this
way uh first we deliver new Ro Center
sustainability manager you will see so
now if you are a dedicated person for
sustainability things you will you will
have your own uh role Center it will be
much easier for you to work with these
features then we added forecast elements
this time scorecards and goals plus we
connected uh sustainability model much
more with the standard business center
Erp features because it was a question
earlier why you have everything
separated as I said we wanted to build
good foundational part but now we are
connected with other features as well so
one of first was if you have Emissions
on your uh incoming invoice why to go to
uh sustainability Journal so now you can
just open your purchase devoice or
purchase order and you can enter your
emissions immediately there
plus with the purchase documents we
enable buying purchase credits so you
can buy purchase credit and immediately
decrease your emissions uh in a system
then we had some new calculation in
sustainability so uh as many of uh users
uh will like to report not different
gases but just carbon equivalent now we
added recalculation from other gases to
carbon deoxide equivalent plus We
additionally added internal carbon fee
because this is required in some
regulation and I I saw that in some
other regulations will come very soon so
you can easily calculate your internal
carbon fee based on your setup plus we
extended uh reporting capabilities this
time we didn't uh make new reports but
we added sustainabilities entries in
finance Financial reports so now you can
easily find uh sustainability entries in
financial reporting I will show this in
the demo plus we added small uh about
City certificates on vendors and items
this is something what can you help uh
in working in some regular job and uh
not in major this is something what will
come in 25.1 we will update demo data
tool so now you have all demo data for
previous features but for all these nice
great new features updated demo tool
will come in November
25.1 so make a first glance on the RO
Center you will see the first place for
what you can find there you can find
master data related with the uh ESG
documents and journal reports analyzis
then a lot of kpis different kpi from
daily and monthly emissions realiz
emissions versus baselines or versus
targets tracking all three different
emissions plus additional Insight
through chars with emission per scope
and
gas then we have purchase documents as I
mentioned and what is important we
didn't want to uh um make any difference
for users who will not use
sustainability features at all or for
the user who do not want to use
sustainability uh features uh into uh
purchase documents so when you open uh
busy Central you will not see any
difference it will be business usual but
if you want to use uh sustainability
features into uh purchase documents you
need to go to sustainability setup and
to find a procurement uh fast tab use
emissions in purchase documents once you
enable you can easily find all necessary
information your purchase uh
lines okay now I want to show you this
in a
demo okay now as I said we have this new
beautiful uh Ro Center sustainability
manager you can find a lot of important
information for example here in headline
you have uh daily kpis uh comparing your
carbon footprint uh today carbon
footprint with yesterday then you have
activities in in this month about all
three gases emissions in current month
then your goals
realized um percentage for all three
gases and uh comparing with your targets
and uh realize versus Baseline I will
explain you now how you will get this
information and plus we have these
insights with the nice charts okay but
now focus on these goals
here uh how we have them we have
sustainability scorecards you can Define
as many scorecards as you want uh I will
use this one this is very simplify table
you just need to configure name and um
number and who is owner if you want to
configure owner you need to have marked
sustainability manager fied for this
user so this is only one important thing
for uh for using to be owner in
sustainability scorecard then for each
of sustainability scorecards you can
find sustainability
goals again you can Define as many goals
as you want there is no limitation only
one can be Main and when I say only one
not only one per scorecard only one in
company can be main goal and now let's
look this one I have goal for Q2 2024
and I have Baseline in first quarter and
the second quarter I have starting and
ending date so now what I have for
Baseline automatically calculated for
what I have in a sustainability entries
in this first quarter for three classes
and then I have current values for this
uh between start and ending date here
this is how system calculated realize
versus Baseline but plus yes we have
unit of measure but plus you have here
place there manually can be enter Target
value for this period so you have three
different you have Baseline in previous
period or period you want to track then
you have what is a current what is
already posted and what is Target for
your current period and this this is
place where you can configure if this is
main goal or not only details from main
goal will be shown on your or Center so
this is first part what we have and uh
yes one small thing as you can imagine
maybe you will have dozens of different
goals you can click show my goals or
show all goals so it can be easily uh if
you have different uh responsibility
persons related with
sustainability so um this is about R
Center and part of forecasting let's
look in additional
calculations now we have a mission fees
new uh page table where you can
configure for each of emission types you
can set again starting date ending date
uh and yes you can configure per
different country per different
responsibility Center or for whole
company so you can make combination and
for each of them for each of them for
carbon you can Define carbon fee this is
internal calculation and you can define
specific carbon equivalent factors so
now we have for carbon uh carbon to
carbon equivalent is all the time one
and this is something what we enter
ourself so if I add for
example um different for additional
country I want for example to add for
United
States and I can say okay for example
emission fee is 35 so this is possible
to be
used um what is important maybe we
started as you maybe started with the
previous features without having
emission fees and now you want to update
existing uh entries because you you
didn't have this functionality earlier
so now if I click update carbon fees
system will update all existing actually
all depends on filter you use but I will
use for all of them and if you say okay
what I will get here carbon fee emission
updated 34 from 34 entries so now I have
emission fee already here and um if I
look in um
entries you will see that we have
updated uh carbon fee here and plus we
have carbon equivalent emission for
carbon equ equivalent emission that
means we have complex uh formula using
all these um um coefficients in emission
fees to recalculate for each of um
entries especially if you can have uh
much more complicated for example here
we have not only for carbon we have for
methan for other gases so system need to
recalculate for all of
them okay um now let's make a look what
we have in our purchase
documents if you look in a purchase
documents you can see we have not only
sustainability we have sustainability
but we have some finance things here as
well and we have
purchase when you look in sustainability
you will see all new existing features
and new features are here let's make
different approach we will not click
here on purchase invoices as even if
they can do it but as you can see we
have ongoing
purchase um we have more purchase
documents purchase invoices for
example we have five but here you can
see only two why two syst will show in
these tiles only purchase documents
related with some of um somehow with the
sustainability so if you have a regular
purchase these purchase documents voices
orders will not be visible in these
tiles so this is much easier for user
who are working with sustainability they
will see only um documents related with
sustainability but first do not forget
we need to have uh enable usage of
purchase document sustainability setup
and now I have for example electricity
uh in I got invoice from my power plant
and what I need to do I need to add
sustainability account number this is
purchase electricity and
then okay regular I need to put my cost
what I have on invoice and here I have
emissions depend what you got in voice
if you have emission for different gases
you can add for all of them you can see
there are all three gases here but if
you got only for carbon deoxide you can
enter only for carbon dioxide um if you
look in a preview
posting this is regular document but you
have sustainability Ledger entries here
in a a find entries so you will see
everything is here document type now
will not be empty this is invoice as
this is related with invo and you will
see all these details emissions will be
as we have in a
document uh what I wanted to emphasize
here uh emissions will when you enter
here emission it will be total emission
for this uh for this line but we have
Fields emission per unit of measure so
if you have for example items or
something different or you have 10 here
system will you will enter full emission
amount but system will calculate per
unit of
measure additional uh purchase document
I want to show you is about carbon
credit before going to carbon uh posting
carbon credit I just want to show how
you need to Mark carbon credit
we will open this one this is standard
item you can see I just have description
carbon credit 3 metric tons of carbon
dioxide and you will find here
sustainability um fast tab what you need
to do you need to mark this is uh
greenhouse gases credit and you need to
enter how much a unit of measure because
this is a three metric tons but in
sustainability setup we said that we are
tracking per kilog so we need to say
okay this one uh piece of carbon credit
is about 3,000 of kilog so you do not
need to enter nothing manually in the
documents you just need to say okay I
bought one or three and system will
automatically calculate based on this
information uh how much you will
decrease so now you can see here carbon
credit I have again sustainability
account number this is about carbon
credit and then system automatically
calculate uh what we have on our item
card again we can post or show POS in
preview if you post a
document we can see here find
entries and again we will have
sustainability Ledger entry this time
document type will be Greenhouse guas
credit and we have all the details as
for any other entry but what is
important here here in emission carbon
you have in minus so what is important
you do not need to enter minus in a
document you just need to enter a
regular number system will automatically
when system recognize this is credit
system will automatically posst this
with a minus value in your
sustainability Ledger
entry what else I wanted to show you
this time reporting capabilities as as I
mentioned now we have infal reporting I
created one report for you
so I have here ESG report I first wanted
to show you how it look like in a row
definition this is very simplify one I
have emission scope one here and what we
added in totaling totaling types I have
now sustainability accounts and I enter
filter from 1100 to
11999 and the row type is not change but
in amount types we can use carbon
equivalent and carbon fee so can use
these two options uh for reporting then
I have for emission two emission three
carbon credit here as we B some carbon
credit then um we are using formulas
emission fee as I said this is carbon
fee then what I'm using here I want to
show because in future reporting for
csrd and some other regulatory reports
you need to use some other um
information not only from sustainability
entries there are some uh important
information you can use statistic
accounts you can use from financials so
you can enter for example number of
employees you can enter put your revenue
from posting accounts and now I want to
calculate emission per employee per
Revenue this is just one
example so once when you run this you
can see okay I have emissions per this
period per previous period I have
everything calculated properly emplo
number of employees you can see
different number per different period
and the revenue and now I have emission
per employee emission per Revenue so you
can use this is just one of example but
you can now you can get much more
capabilities for reporting we will
continue to invest in reporting um maybe
a little bit different but this is
definitely something what we are looking
for the future about sustainabilities
and what I wanted to show on on the end
uh I mentioned we have
certificates certificates is not
something specifically that you can use
you can use for any type of um
certificat for vendor or for items for
example if this item is uh top green
without using any emission in production
you want to know this because you want
to know what you are selling the same
situation is if your vendor is carbon
negative you can configure that this
this vendor is uh U number one the best
in um sustainability in ESG so you can
use for many different things this is on
you how you will use certificate
you can use standard certificate using
your search or your all Center but and
you can Define if this certificate is
for item or for vendor but you can
create directly from item or vendor card
so currently I do not have if I click
new you will see type is automatically
populated with item if I do this from
vendor side C will automatically
prepopulate the vendor now I can say
okay this
is green
name green certificate I have some area
I already created so now we have
additional tables with area we have
additional with the standard so you can
choose different areas so you can group
them uh based on what you want to track
you can uh keep different standards if
is
contoso and now if this certificate has
some value so if you are tracking for
example about emissions or something
like that whatever you want to track you
can enter if you do not want it will be
empty but if you want if it has value
you can choose has value and then you
can enter for example five and you can
add this is basic small feature and
applicable both uh items and
vendors so this is what I want to show
you the demo there are small things here
and there you will you will see much
more when you start to test but now I
want to come back to my presentation and
to show one more thing and this is what
I want to show you call for Action in
general for you now this is not that we
have this functionality embedded in a
busy Center yes we already started
previous fa now we uh en Reach This
functionality we will continue with
investment in sustainability features
but what is important here um few months
ago uh busy Central has been added uh
to uh Microsoft cloud for sustainability
so now if you go you have this link when
you go to Microsoft cloud for
sustainability you can find our bigger
solution for Enterprises um Microsoft um
uh sustainability manager this is for uh
big uh functionality for big Enterprises
but now as a solution for smbs or smc's
you can find micros Dynamic C5 busy
Central as well so here you can see
there you can directly go to our
documentation you can read so this is
important this is now not only for bus
Central users so any user who trying to
find some solution only for
sustainability even if they are not
focused on Erp at all they can find B
Central a sustainability option so this
is my last message I wanted to share
with you in um this session so you are
more than welcome to try uh to find uh
try to test all these features in
preview as the majority of them actually
all all of them except demo data will
come with a major version
25 uh demo data will come with the next
minor 25 5.1 so you can easily test all
these new features thank you